Robert Ottogalli

Austin, TX 78739 • ottogalli.robert@gmail.com • +1-732-237-6892 LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/robert-ottogalli/ GitHub: https://github.com/Rob-Ottogalli

SUMMARY

Software engineer and data analyst with 7 years' experience as a project manager localizing 20+ languages. Native English speaker, fluent in Italian, Spanish, working proficiency in French. Successfully managed client relationships and a global network of providers to provide translations of marketing and user assistance documentation into 20+ languages in the technology, life sciences, and healthcare sectors. Tracked and delivered multiple projects concurrently in a fast-paced, high-growth environment. Masters' candidate in Computer and Information Technology.

SKILLS

- Java 11, Python 3.6, HTML, SQL, PowerBI, Tableau, Pandas, Matplotlib, MongoDB
- Data Structures, Algorithms, Object Oriented Programming, Extract-Transform-Load, Visualize
- Project Management, Data Analysis, Business Intelligence, Customer Service
- Written Communication, Verbal Communication
- Computer-Assisted Translation (CAT) tools including RWS WorldServer, MemoQ, Tridion Docs
- Advanced Microsoft Word, Advanced Microsoft Excel, PowerPoint, Adobe Lightroom

PROGRAMMING PROJECTS

- Data Analysis Project on Demographic Impact on Common Health Risks: Final group project for Data Analysis Bootcamp. A full stack app containing Tableau analysis of demographics and leading health risks in the United States, stored in SQL database, synthesized from 7 million records in CDC vital statistics data, with predictive analysis powered by a Neural Network.
 - o https://github.com/Rob-Ottogalli/demographic impact on health risks
- Natural Language Processing (Italian Verb Conjugator): A Natural Language Processing project: a rule-based Python program that correctly conjugates all forms of any verb in Italian.
 - o https://github.com/Rob-Ottogalli/Italian_Verb_Conjugator

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

RWS Group. Valued at \$936 million in 2020, RWS Group is the world's leading provider of technology-enabled language, content management and intellectual property services.

Senior Project Manager: January 2021 – Present

- Led a team of 12 people to ensure quality and timelines of team's deliveries, responsiveness, and professional treatment of customers as part of a \$30 million program localizing content for a Fortune 10 client
- Supported the business unit by developing a Python script to perform ETL on data sets. Prepared
 visualization dashboards and decks for quarterly and monthly presentation to clients. Conducted
 ad-hoc data pulls and trend analysis for internal cross-team managers (non-data audience)

Welocalize, Inc. Welocalize is the 9th largest global language services provider at \$256+ million revenue in 2020, delivering multilingual content transformation services in translation, localization, and adaptation for over 250 languages.

Project Manager: April 2019 – January 2021

- Partnered with cross-functional teams on concurrent initiatives including to implement localization programs, monitor budget, and oversee production for strategic accounts
- Manage localization projects for life sciences, engineering, and technology clients, including localizing user documentation in XML, audio/multimedia training content, and web content
- Worked with a team to grow a customer account from \$400,000 to \$1 million in annual revenue over 1.5 years through attention to detail and customer service

CQ fluency. CQ fluency partners with the world's leading healthcare organizations to supply translation and communication solutions in over 170 languages.

Project Manager: June 2017 – November 2018

- Led teams of vendors to plan and execute the formatting, translation, and accessibility of 3+ clients' high-stakes healthcare insurance documentation under tight deadlines, delivering 15+ projects totaling \$100,000 translation revenue per month during peak season
- Partnered with Engineering, Sales, and Production teams to localize client's 100,000-word website
 into Spanish through a dynamic software solution and sold a non-technical client on a technical
 service using easy-to-understand terms verbally, in writing, and via presentations
- Optimized workflow efficiency through technological solutions, saving team up to 30% admin time
- Trained 5 new hires on company tools and workflow procedures

Project Coordinator: September 2014 – June 2017

- Began as Quality Assurance Specialist and was promoted to Project Coordinator.
- Entrusted with 4 of the company's top accounts, made sense of ambiguity, managed expectations, and ensured adherence of deliverables to clients' specifications for 850+ projects

Freelance Translator and Editor: November 2018 – April 2019, 2014 – 2016

- Translated over 300,000 words from Italian, French, and Spanish into English, consisting of television subtitling, press releases, e-commerce, academic transcripts, and personal documents
- Employed human translation and machine translation post-editing workflows

EDUCATION

- Master of Computer and Information Technology (Expected Graduation Date: May2023): University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA.
- Data Analysis and Visualization Boot Camp: University of Texas at Austin Boot Camp, Texas McCombs School of Business, Austin, TX
- Bachelor of Arts (Spanish; Concentration: Translation): Montclair State University, NJ
- Bachelor of Arts (Italian, Classics; Concentration: Literature): Montclair State University, NJ